Finding Aid for James J. Duderstadt Papers 1963-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Paper Documents
  - Topical Files 1971-1991
    - Presentations 1991 (Box 24)
  - Teaching 1971-1981
    The Teaching series (2.5 linear ft., ca. 1971-1981) works hand-in-hand with the Research series. Where the Research series shows Duderstadt's intense interest in scientific discovery, the Teaching series shows how he conveyed this knowledge to a broad audience. The series contains nuclear engineering lecture material and assignments as well as material on seminars taught by Duderstadt such as the UM-Bendix Engineering Summer conference and the Consumer's Power Nuclear Engineering Program that was held in 1980. The series also contains background materials and scripts for the University of Michigan Television Center program "Nuclear Power and You" that was taped in the late 1970s and which featured Duderstadt.
    - Argonne National Laboratory 1975-1979 (Box 17)
    - Class Assignments various dates (Box 17)
    - Commonwealth Associates Reactor Course 1973 (Box 17)
    - Computers in Engineering Education 1980 (Box 17)
    - Course descriptions various dates (Box 17)
    - Course lecture material undated (Box 17)
    - Course material for Nuclear Engineering 441 undated (Box 17)
    - Course material for Nuclear Engineering 511 1970 (Box 17)
    - Course material for Nuclear Engineering 695 undated (Box 17)
    - Energy Forum 1980 (Box 17)
    - General Energy Education workshop 1978 (Box 17)
    - High School Seminars 1973 (Box 17)
    - Lecture Material
      - Undated material (Box 17)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 17)
      - 1975 (Box 17)
      - Development of Nuclear Power 1979 (Box 18)
      - E.C.E. 426: Reactions in Plasma Physics* *or, How not to spend fall weekends in Ann Arbor 1973-1974 (Box 18)
      - Fundamentals of Transport Theory, Ecole D'ete' D'Analyse Numerique June-July, 1981 (Box 18)
      - Inertial Confinement Fusion, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Kinetic Theory 1976 (Box 18)
      - Laser Fusion 1971, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Laser-Plasma 1971 (Box 18)
      - Nuclear Engineering 643 1976, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Nuclear Engineering 644: Transport Theory 1977 (Box 18)
      - Nuclear Engineering Colloquium, Fall 1973 (Box 18)
      - Overheads and Equations circa 1968 (Box 18)
      - Waves, Pulses, and Noise 1966-1969 (Box 18)
    - Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory circa 1971 (Box 18)
    - Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory undated (Box 18)
    - National Aeronautics and Space Administration Intensive Course on Lasers 1972 (Box 18)
    - Nuclear Education Program, Consumer's Power project 1980-1981 (Box 19)
    - Nuclear Engineering Curriculum, scattered dates (Box 19)
    - Nuclear Engineering examinations, various dates (Box 19)
    - N.E. 562 Student Papers 1980 (Box 19)
    - N.E. 599 Student Paper 1971 (Box 19)
    - N.E. Ph.D. Candidates
      - Adalioglu, Ulvi circa 1971 (Box 19)
      - Sidney Karin circa 1971 (Box 19)
      - Russ Mosteller circa 1971 (Box 19)
      - William Price circa 1970 (Box 19)
      - Paul Turinsky circa 1971 (Box 19)
    - Sanoia Comments circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Seminars
      - Inertial Confinement Fusion Schemes circa 1977 (Box 19)
      - Laser-Fusion 1977 (Box 19)
      - Nuclear Power: Realities and Myths circa 1976 (Box 19)
      - The Role of the Finite Element Method in Radiation Physics circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Student Course Evaluations circa 1977 (Box 19)
    - Student Study Guide for Principles of Engineering, undated (Box 19)
    - Summer School on the Transport Equation, Ecole D'ete D'Analyse Numerique circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - UM-Bendix Engineering Summer Conference 1979 (Box 19)
    - University of Michigan Television Center (UMTV), background material for "Nuclear Power and You" program circa 1978 (Box 19)
    - UMTV: "Nuclear Power and You," scripts (Box 19)
    - United States Department of Energy Workshop on General Energy Education circa 1978 (Box 19)
    - Utility Nuclear Engineering Summer Course undated (Box 19)
    - Photographs, 4 envelopes
      - Illustrations used in Publications (Box 19)
      - Neutron Transport Theory Conference, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory 1971 (Box 19)
      - Photographs used in Publications. Computers; data centers; Detroit Edison Plant, Monroe, Michigan; disk storage unit; Enrico Fermi 2, Monroe, Michigan; graphics display unit; magnetic tape unit (Box 19)
      - University of Michigan Computer Laboratory with students, unidentified and undated (Box 19)
      - Slides used in Publications, 5 slides (Box 19)
  - Presidential Transition Files
    The Presidential Transition Files series (2.0 linear feet, ca. 1988) consists largely of the working files of the inauguration committee for the 11th President of the University of Michigan. These files include material on the invitation list, program, seating arrangements and other logistical issues. In addition to working files, the series contains some correspondence to Duderstadt on the announcement of his appointment as 11th President of the University of Michigan, the inauguration address, and thanks you's sent from the Duderstadt's after the inauguration. Newsclippings relating to the inauguration are especially complete and arranged chronologically by month. Also of particular note are printed materials designed especially for the inauguration and related events. Printed material includes the invitation and program
    - Correspondence 1988 (Box 20)
      - Congratulations and Presidential Thank-You's June-September 1988, 10 folders (Box 20)
    - Electronic mail congratulations, paper printouts 1988 (Box 20)
    - Inauguration, (June-October 1988) (Box 21)
      - Acceptances (Box 21)
      - Address (Box 21)
      - Committee, Working Papers September 27, 1988 (Box 21)
      - Correspondence (Box 21)
      - Delegates (Box 21)
      - Hill Auditorium (Box 21)
      - Ingalls Reception (Box 21)
      - Invitation Lists (Box 21)
      - Recommendations for, 2 folders
      - Invitation Sub-Committee (Box 21)
      - Logistics (Box 21)
      - Marshalls (Box 21)
      - Power Center Reception (Box 21)
      - Preparation, Task List and Assignments (Box 21)
      - Printed Materials (e.g. Invitation, Schedule of Events, Program) (Box 21)
      - Program (Box 21)
      - Regent's Luncheon (Box 21)
      - Remarks by C.M. Vest (Box 21)
      - Seating Plans (Box 21)
      - Student Events (Box 21)
      - Thank you's (post inauguration) (Box 21)
    - News Coverage June-October 1988, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Strategic Planning, 1986-1996
    The series Strategic Planning (.75 linear feet, 1986-1996) includes materials mainly from the first few years of Duderstadt's presidential tenure. This series includes background materials on the Michigan Mandate and Michigan Plan as well as reference notebooks used in strategic planning meetings. Related strategic planning material can be found in the Strategy series within the Digital Documents Subgroup.
    - Diversity Readings, general, scattered dates. (Box 23)
    - Faculty Diversity, University of California Study September 1987 (Box 23)
    - Michigan Commitment, background materials, ca. 1988 (Box 23)
    - Michigan Mandate and related materials, ca. 1988, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Michigan Plan, presentation and associated materials, ca. 1988 (Box 23)
    - Strategy Files, general, ca. 1988 (Box 23)
    - Strategic Planning
      - Reference Notebooks, ca. 1986-1996, 3 folders; 2 volumes (Box 23)
      - Summary Notes on Schools and Colleges, ca. 1985-1986 (Box 23)
    - Strategic Planning Team, Agendas and Meeting Minutes circa 1987-1988 (Box 23)
- Digital Documents 1986-1997, 2144 digital files 160.5 MB
  There are 2,144 digital files (160.5 MB) in the Digital Documents subgroup. At the time of the records accession to the Bentley Historical Library, the Macintosh operating system version 8.0 was in use. The original organization and arrangement of Duderstadt's digital files has been preserved. Duderstadt maintained seven archival directories: Speeches, Idea Files, Strategy, Position Papers, Presentations, Write Files, and Legacy. An additional series, Digital Images, was created when a collection of digital images of university building projects was accessioned to the collection early in 1998.
  The arrangement of files within each directory is chronological by date starting with the 1986-1987 school year. This arrangement was designed and used by Duderstadt in the Speeches, Idea Files, and Write Files series and extended to the remaining series except the Digital Images during the processing phase of the project. The directory naming scheme effectively describes the type of record contained within the directory. File names are also in most cases descriptive of the content, however, researchers should note that Duderstadt used personal last names, initials, abbreviations, and numerous acronyms in naming files. A list of commonly used acronyms and abbreviations used for file naming purposes can be found in the "Additional Descriptive Data" section of the finding aid. Researcher's Note: The file-naming scheme also reveals the specific version of a particular document. Duderstadt maintained the file name for the record and added a sequence of numbers to the file name to indicate various versions. For example, the record "Project Athena" progresses from Project Athena .92, Project Athena 1.0, 1.01, 1.2, 2.1, to Project Athena 2.21.
  - Speeches 1986-1996
    A main avenue President Duderstadt utilized as a means to communicate his ideas, objectives, and university strategic plan was to get out into the community and talk. During his presidency, Duderstadt frequently made several speeches a day to groups on campus and across the state, thus making the Speeches series (821 files, 1986-1996) the largest series in the Digital Documents subgroup. The early speech files from the years 1986 to 1992 were predominately composed using the MORE 3.1 outline program. However, after 1992 he drafted his speeches using a combination of MORE 3.1 and Microsoft Word 6.0. Major Speeches contained in this series include: The Cranbrook Address, The Challenge of K-12 Education, February, 1990, American Nuclear Society Keynote Address, A Future of Change, April, 1992, State Equity in Education Conference, The Michigan Mandate: A Progress Report, March, 1993, Vision 2017: The Third Century, November, 1993.
    Researchers should note that a list of key speeches by title, year, and location can be found in the digital file titled "Accomplishments" located in the Strategy series. Also, note that several iterations of particular speeches can be found in the Digital Documents subgroup. Duderstadt's file naming scheme reflects the change in a file by a series of numbers located after the file name.
    - 1986-1987 Speeches, 37 digital files
    - 1987-1988 Speeches, 54 digital files
    - 1988-1989 Speeches, 124 digital files
    - 1989-1990 Speeches, 132 digital files
    - 1990-1991 Speeches, 214 digital files
    - 1991-1992 Speeches, 52 digital files
    - 1992-1993 Speeches, 36 digital files
    - 1994-1995 Speeches, 27 digital files
    - 1995-1996 Speeches, 135 digital files
    - Athletic Talks-Speeches, 12 digital files
  - Idea Files 1986-1995, 328 digital files
    The Idea Files series (328 digital files, 1986-1995) is comprised of files created with the MORE 3.1 outline program. Many of the outline files in this series resemble a silhouette of ideas that Duderstadt later developed into strategic planning documents, position papers, and speeches. Other outlines in the series read as talking points Duderstadt used either to prepare for a meeting or an important conversation. Major topics addressed in this series include higher education, teaching and research, information technology, and affirmative action. Yearly progress reports on the status of Duderstadt's agenda and goals can be found within this series in files with titles such as "Summary 1991-92" or "The Year Past." Researchers interested in additional biographical material should consult the digital file "Biography" in the 1988-1989 Ideas subseries and the Biographical series in the Paper Documents subgroup.
    - 1986-1987 Ideas, 36 digital files (Box 1)
      [RESTRICTED until July 1, 2030 ]
    - 1987-1988 Ideas, 28 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989 Ideas, 33 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 Ideas, 47 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 Ideas, 29 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 Ideas, 20 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 Ideas, 30 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 Ideas, 57 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 Ideas, 31 digital files (Box 1)
  - Strategy 1986-1997, 63 digital files
    While the other series in the Duderstadt Digital Documents subgroup contain records which cover a variety of topics, the Strategy series (84 files, 1986-1996) is largely focused on issues specifically related to President Duderstadt's vision of higher education in the 21st century. The framework for his position of the future of education can be found in two key documents: "Vision 2000: The Leaders and Best" and "Vision 2017: Transforming the University."
    Duderstadt's espousal of the changing environment and the need for traditional institutions to transform is captured in this series. A researcher interested in his views on organizational change should look at the files containing the word transformation or variants with "trans" such as, "Transformation Text 1.6," "Trans Team 2.0," and "Trans Course 2.1." For a summary of Duderstadt's major strategic initiatives, priorities for the coming decade, and views of changes needed in education, research, and diversity consult the file "The Decade Report." This report outlines major initiatives introduced to the university by Duderstadt such as the Institute for the Humanities, the Media Union, Institute of Molecular Medicine, and the Tauber Manufacturing Institute. The digital file titled "Accomplishments," written in the fall of 1995, provides a very informative outline of Duderstadt's priorities for the decade, accomplishments, projects (listed by year), strategic plan (Phases I, II, III), major papers, and selected speeches (listed by year). Lastly, this series contains in the 1996-1997 Strategy subseries the records related to Duderstadt's vision of "The New University" and "The Millennium Project."
    - 1986-1997 Strategy, 63 digital files on 1 CD-ROM (Box 1)
  - Position Papers 1986-1997
    The Position Papers series (140 digital files, 1986-1997) contains Duderstadt's key addresses, white papers, planning documents, annual reports, and presidential essays. Major papers contained in this series include: "The Michigan Mandate: A Strategic Linking of Academic Excellence and Social Diversity," "The Role of the Research University in Undergraduate Education," "Michigan's Challenge: Preparing for an Age of Knowledge," "The Michigan Agenda for Women: Toward a Full and Equal Partnership," "Intellectual Transformation." A complete list of major position papers can be found in the digital file titled "Accomplishments" located in the Strategy series. Researchers will note that several versions of a document are in the Digital Documents subgroup, and that Duderstadt used a numbering scheme to organize versions of an digital document. One example of his file naming scheme is a series of files from the 1991-1996 subseries entitled "Women 3.2," "Women 3.3," "Women 3.4."
    - 1986-1991 Position Papers, 74 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1991-1997 Position Papers, 66 digital files (Box 1)
  - Presentations 1987-1997, 64 digital files
    The majority of records in the Presentations series (64 digital files, 1987-1996) were created using the software application PowerPoint by Microsoft. This application was designed specifically as a presentation tool. Many of the records in this series seem to be presentations given to Duderstadt's Executive Officers (EOs) and the Regents at retreat meetings (for example, "Regents Retreat," "Tuition Retreat," "Leadership Retreat"). Other presentation topics included in this series are The Michigan Mandate, The Mission Plan, and University Resources.
    Researchers will note that in the Digital Documents subgroup contextual and descriptive information such as audience, location, and exact date of the presentation or speech is not always explicit in the digital record.
    - 1987-1997 Presentations files, 64 digital files
  - Write Files 1988-1997
    The Write Files series (588 digital files, 1987-1997) is composed entirely of Microsoft Word text files. Researchers will find a variety of "traditional" business formats such as correspondence, agendas, and memorandums contained within the Write Files series. However, note that there is often an absence of descriptive information, such as the receiver's name and address, date, and signature line. The absence of this information is a reflection of the distributive work process practiced in President Duderstadt's office--a process afforded by networked computer technology. The correspondence includes letters of recommendation, thank-you's, and communication to persons not only at the University of Michigan but to persons throughout the country including U.S. presidents Gerald Ford and George Bush and Michigan governors James Blanchard and John Engler. It is important to note that Duderstadt often used the recipient's name or initials to name the file. For example, "Blanchard-1/89" and "H & V-11/10" are communications to Governor James Blanchard in January 1989 and Harold and Vivian Shapiro on November 10th respectively.
    - 1988 and earlier Write Files, 19 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989 Write Files, 19 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 Write Files, 50 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 Write Files, 74 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 Write Files, 54 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 Write Files, 120 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 Write Files, 114 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 Write Files, 55 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 Write Files, 75 digital files (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 Write Files, 8 digital files (Box 1)
  - Legacy Documents circa 1996, 36 digital files
    The Legacy Documents series (36 digital files, ca. 1996) contains the drafts of the digital records that resulted in a number of printed publications written by Duderstadt together entitled "Legacy Documents." The files in the "Sunflower" sub-folder are those files that resulted in the publication entitled A Growing Season: A Report from the President.. .The University of Michigan, 1986-1996. A complete set of printed "Legacy" documents including A Growing Season... is in the Paper Documents series Publications.
    - Legacy Documents
  - Digital Images, circa 1996
    The Digital Images series (55 digital files, ca. 1996) provides a look at the many buildings either newly constructed or renovated during Duderstadt's presidential tenure at Michigan. The Ann Arbor campus underwent major changes to the Central, North, Athletic, and Medical campuses. New construction projects include the Media Union, Cancer & Geriatrics Center, Medical Science Research Building, Lurie Engineering Center and Bell Tower, Donald Canham Natatorium, and the Glenn E. Schembechler Hall. Major renovation and improvement projects include Angell Hall, CC Little, Chemistry Building, and Health Service. Included in this series are images of the buildings constructed on the U-M Dearborn and Flint campuses. A complete listing of all construction and renovation projects is highlighted in a special booklet titled Rebuilding the University, The University of Michigan 1986-1996. A copy of this document is in the Paper Documents series Publications.
    - Digital Images, 55 digital files (Box 1)
Acronyms and Abbreviations used by Duderstadt
AA - Ann Arbor
aaac - Academic Affairs Advisory Committee
AAAC - Academic Affairs Advisory Council
AAPS - Ann Arbor Public Schools
AAU - Association of American Universities
ADA - American Disability Act
APG - Academic Policy Group
ASB - Academic Service Board
ASIS - American Society for Information Science
BAM - Black Action Movement
BPC - Budget Priorities Committee
CAEN - Computer Aided Engineering Network
CAEOT - The Center for Advanced Electronics and Optics
CEW - Center for the Continuing Education for Women
CIC - Center for Institutional Cooperation
COMU - Council on a Multicultural University
CRIM - Center for Research on Integrated Manufacturing
CRLT - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching
CUE - Committee on Undergraduate Education
ECE - Electrical and Computer Engineering
EECS - College of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science
EO - Executive Officer
ERIM - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan
EVPHA - Executive Vice President for Health Affairs
EXPRES - Experimental Research in Electronic Submission Project
GTA - Graduate Teaching Assistants
GUIR - Government University Industry Research Roundtable
ICPSR - Inter - University Consortium for Political and Social Research
ICR - Indirect Cost Rate
IOs - Inputs and Outputs
IPPS - Institute for Public Policy Studies
ISR - Institute for Social Research
ITD - Information Technologies Division
ITI - Industrial Technology Institute
ITIC - The Integrated Technology Instructional Center
LSA - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts
MBRT - Michigan Business Round Table
MERIT - Michigan Educational Research Information Triad
MET - Michigan Education Trust
MITN - Michigan Information Technology Network
MLK - Martin Luther King
MM - The Michigan Mandate
MSU - Michigan State University
NASA - National Air and Space Administration
NASULGC - National Association of State Universities and Land Grand Colleges
NEH - National Endowment for the Humanities
NSF - National Science Foundation
NSB - National Science Board
OAA - Office of Academic Affairs
OIP - Office of International Programs
OUE - Office of University Events
OVPR - Office of Vice President for Research
PACMA - Presidential Advisory Committee on Minority Affairs
PAG - President's Advisory Group
PIF - Presidential Initiatives Fund
RAG - Research Advisory Group
REF - Research Excellence Fund
SACUA - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs
SBR - State Budget Request
SILS - School of Information and Library Science
SRCC - Semiconductor Research Corporation Center
SPRL - Space Physics Research Laboratory
SPT - Strategic Planning Team
UEF - University Endowment Fund
UG - Undergraduate Student
UMS - University Musical Society
UMMA - University of Michigan Museum of Art
VPGR - Vice President Government Relations
VPSA - Vice President for Student Affairs
WAM - Women at Michigan
WISE - Women in Science and Engineering
Sources Consulted in Preparing the Finding Aid
"Biography," May 19, 1989, Ideas Series, [Digital Document], James J. Duderstadt Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.
"Biographical Data," May 1, 1987, Box 1, James J. Duderstadt Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.
"Background Information," June 9, 1988, Box 1, James J. Duderstadt Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.
"Inauguration 1.9S," October 5, 1988, Speeches Series, [Digital Document], James J. Duderstadt Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.
"Opening Remarks: Idles of March," not dated, Box 8, James J. Duderstadt Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.
"Farewell Address," April 7, 1986, Box 8, James J. Duderstadt Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.
"Michigan Mandate 3.0," October 28, 1990, Speeches Series, [Digital Document], James J. Duderstadt Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.